DELICIOUS IN DUNGEON
《迷宮飯》
Dammit!
可惡！
What the hell?
搞什麼？
This wall wasn't here on our way down!
我們來的時候沒有這道牆啊！
Another earthquake?
又地震了嗎？
Not an earthquake.
這不是地震
The dungeon is shifting and changing its layout.
是迷宮在移動，更改樣貌
It's probably that magician's doing.
我猜應該是那個魔術師搞的鬼
Maybe he's on the lookout for us.
他或許是在提防我們吧
You mean he's been making us wander around in circles this whole time?
你的意思是他讓我們 一直在原地打轉？
Maybe it's worth taking a little risk.
稍微冒個險好了
Give me a minute.
等我一下
It's gone now.
好像走了
Climbing over walls might not be a smart move.
翻牆也許不是聰明的選擇
Guess we'll have to pick our way out.
只好踏實地找出路了
Anyway, is it just me…
話說回來，總覺得這裡…
or is the city starting to bustle?
好像漸漸熱鬧起來了？
With the Red Dragon dead,
炎龍死後
the lurking monsters are starting to show themselves.
原本保持低調的魔物都跑出來了
This level was originally crawling with monsters.
這一層原本就有很多魔物
We're lucky we didn't bump into any until now.
至今都沒碰上算我們好運
Hey, are you okay?
喂，沒事吧？
This isn't good.
這樣不健全
We've been trekking without a break,
大家不停趕路，自從吃了龍後
and we haven't had a decent meal since that Dragon.
就沒吃過像樣的一餐
How old is Laios?
萊歐斯幾歲啊？
I'm not sure if he's getting up there or still in his youth,
不曉得他算年紀大還是年輕
but Chilchuck and Marcille are likely still growing.
但奇爾查克和瑪露希爾大概還在發育
Come on.
振作點
It's downright shameful not being able to provide them with proper meals.
竟無法讓正值發育期的他們吃飽 老夫實在是太慚愧了
I must feed them.
必須讓他們吃東西
The youngsters must be fed.
要讓年輕人進食才行
I must feed them!
必須設法餵飽他們！
What's that sweet smell?
有種甜甜的氣味
Is it food?
是食物的味道嗎？
No, it smells like flowers.
不是，比較像是花香
Where there are flowers, there's usually water.
有開花的地方通常周遭就會有水
Track it down for us, Chil!
去找一下吧，奇爾！
On it!
收到！
Is this place a graveyard or something?
這裡是墓地之類的嗎？
Wait, someone's there.
等等，那裡有人
Don't look!
不能看！
W-We beg your pardon.
真是失禮了
Hey, Senshi! Let go of me!
喂，先西！放開我！
Get back, Senshi!
快後退，先西！
What's this?
這是什麼？
Draw your weapon!
拿起武器！
These creatures aren't human.
這些傢伙不是人類
They're Dryad flowers!
是樹精花！
Then what's this body fluid?
那麼這些體液是什麼？
It was not a liquid.
那並不是液體
Tiny particles entered the body through the respiratory system,
這些細微粒子從呼吸器官進入體內後
sticking to the mucous membrane.
會沾附在黏膜上
The body recognized these particles as poison
身體會將這些熟悉的 粒子判斷為有毒物質
and kicked the immune system into gear, immediately attempting to flush them out.
激發免疫系統，開始迅速將其排出
This is known as…
也就是所謂的…
hay fever.
花粉症
Ugh, gross!
好噁心，有夠髒的！
It hurts!
好痛！
It's the Dryads' pollen!
原來是樹精花粉！
This is bad. Don't breathe it!
這下不妙了，別吸入花粉！
This isn't good.
情況很糟糕
I can't stop crying.
眼淚流不停
Get up!
站起來！
Pull yourself together, Senshi!
振作點啊，先西！
Laios!
萊歐斯！
-Kensuke… -Dammit!
-劍助… -可惡！
My eyes are acting up too…
我的眼睛也開始…
Senshi, reach out your hand!
先西，把手往前伸！
On three, use it to strike behind you!
聽我數完三聲，就把劍用力往後砍！
One,
一…
two…
二…
Three!
三！
Damn, my eyes are starting to itch too.
不妙啊，我的眼睛也開始癢了
I can't see.
眼前一片模糊
Run, Senshi!
快逃啊，先西！
No!
不行！
It is my duty to protect the youngsters!
老夫必須保護年輕人！
Are you serious?
你在說什麼啊？
Chilchuck!
奇爾查克！
Be my eyes!
你來當老夫的眼睛！
I can't. I can't see anything!
不行，我什麼都看不見！
You have sharper senses!
你不是有敏銳的感官嗎？
Smell?
靠氣味？
No, the smell of pollen is too overpowering.
行不通，花粉的氣味太強烈了
Hearing?
聲音呢？
Senshi's sneezing too loud.
先西的噴嚏聲有夠吵
I can't rely on my sight, smell, or hearing.
視覺、嗅覺、聽覺都靠不住
The wind!
是風！
It avoided your sneeze and retreated diagonally to the right.
敵人躲開噴嚏，逃到右邊的斜後方了
Senshi, swing up now!
舉劍揮下去，先西！
Kensuke…
劍助…
My staff is completely broken in half.
魔杖徹底斷成兩半了
I've got to mend it and infuse it with magic quickly before it withers away.
要是不快點修補、注入魔力 魔杖會乾枯的
It took me years to nurture it to its current state…
我花那麼長的歲月才培養到這麼大…
I-It's safe in there.
這裡面很安全喔
Don't lie!
少騙人！
You fought against Dryad flowers?
你們跟樹精花打過？
That must've been tough.
想必是場硬仗吧
I didn't think they were flower monsters.
老夫萬萬沒想到對方是花的魔物
I totally thought they were male and female humans.
當下完全誤認成人類男女
Dryads are unisexual flowers,
樹精是單性花
so you're right about them being male and female.
所以有分雌雄的說法並沒有錯
Just maybe…
說不定…
What will you do about him?
要拿他怎麼辦？
Shouldn't we stop him by force?
是不是用拳頭阻止他比較好？
But we can't afford to be picky anymore.
但我們也差不多沒得挑剔了
At this point, does it really matter if the flower resembles a human?
即使花是人的外型 事到如今又何必在意？
Marci--
瑪露希…
I found some!
我找到囉！
Dryad fruits!
是樹精果實！
How to turn back time…
如何讓時間回溯…
Stop hunting for shady magic like it's no big deal!
住手啦，別自然地找 那種感覺很危險的魔法！
Your black magic jokes aren't funny!
你開的黑魔法玩笑，我笑不出來啊！
The last Dryad I took out didn't release any pollen.
最後砍死的樹精沒有噴出花粉
It must've been a female flower.
那應該是雌花吧
Flowers before pollination care for and protect their fruits.
授粉前的花會負責照顧並保護果實
I found some more fruit-like things over here.
這邊也有像是果實的東西
Those are buds.
那是花蕾
They'll eventually grow into Dryad flowers.
花蕾長大後就會成為樹精花
These seem easier to eat than those fruits.
跟剛才的果實比起來 這看起來比較好入口
They might be pretty tasty.
或許會很好吃
Let's harvest them.
採收下來吧
Don't pick too many.
別採太多喔
Okay.
好
There are Mandrakes here.
有長曼德拉草耶
We don't have time to get a dog,
我們沒空準備狗
so I'll just chop its head off if you don't mind.
你不介意我把頭砍下來吧？
Shut up. When are you going to let me live that down?
你很煩耶，是要刻意提幾次啊？
It's a pretty decent harvest.
真是大豐收啊
Good thing I borrowed an axe from the orcs!
跟半獸人借斧頭是正確的決定！
Put the chopped ingredients into a pot with water and let it stew.
把砍碎的食材和水一起加進鍋裡燉煮
When the ingredients are soft, remove from heat
將其煮軟後把火熄滅
and mash them inside the pot.
在鍋裡搗碎食材
Once they turn into a paste, add more water and seasoning.
搗成泥狀後再次加水並調味
Smells delightful.
好香啊
I have an idea.
想到一個主意了
Sauté them lightly with butter and throw in some mushrooms.
用奶油稍微炒一下，加入蘑菇
Pour melted cheese on top,
在上頭淋上融化的起司
and it's done!
就完成了！
JACK-O'-LANTERN POTAGE AND SAUTÉED DRYAD BUDS WITH CHEESE
（傑克燈籠濃湯與樹精起司煎花蕾）
Did you have to put the soup in that?
為何用那個裝湯？
I thought it might aid in restoring your magic a little.
這樣或許能多補充一些魔力
Don't think you can excuse it just because you meant well.
別以為仗著善意行事就能被寬恕
I'll try it, though.
雖然我還是會吃啦
It's sweet!
好甜喔！
It has a light floral fragrance.
有淡淡的花香
It's rich and creamy, but melts in your mouth.
明明味道濃稠卻入口即化
I love this.
我喜歡這個
What an appalling sight.
這景象真是嚇人
The sourness of the cheese pairs nicely with this.
和起司的酸味很搭耶
I like the bitter tang the buds have.
老夫喜歡它帶有些微苦味
Anyway, how do we even get out of this dungeon?
話說回來，我們要怎樣做才能脫困？
What if we never find our way out?
會不會就這樣永遠出不去？
If all the routes to the surface are blocked,
完全封鎖通往地表的道路
it would disrupt the flow of magic, so that's unlikely.
會斷絕魔力的流動 所以我認為不太可能發生
There has to be a way out somewhere.
一定還有其他出路才對
Are there any patterns to the shifts in the dungeon?
迷宮的變化會不會有什麼規律？
There must be!
一定會有！
Let's note down the timings and locations of the rumblings.
我們試著記錄地鳴的週期和地點吧
I'm starting to feel hopeful.
我開始覺得有希望了
A full stomach does wonders for optimism, doesn't it?
肚子填飽後就會變得比較樂觀呢
I'm starting to feel warmer.
身體暖和起來了
I think some of my magic is returning.
魔力好像有恢復一點
Laios and Senshi, I need to heal your injuries.
也得治療萊歐斯和先西的傷呢
You shouldn't overexert yourself.
你還是別勉強比較好
I won't.
我不會勉強
Laios, you'll be the one doing the work.
萊歐斯，由你來努力
I'll teach you some magic.
我會教你魔法
I can't protect all of you from the lunatic magician by myself.
只憑我一個人無法保護 所有人不受狂亂魔術師傷害
If you can use healing and defense magic, it would help a lot.
你如果能使用 治療或防禦魔法會輕鬆許多
Falin has taught you the basics, right?
法琳有教過你基礎對吧？
Sort of.
是沒錯啦
She specializes in the gnome magic system,
她專精於地精魔法體系
which is a bit different from the one I use.
和我使用的魔法體系有些不同
But the fundamentals are similar, so you'll catch on.
但根源都差不多，所以不用擔心
I'll drum it into you in no time.
我馬上教到你會
We need to become stronger.
我們必須變強
Those two are too optimistic.
他們也太積極了吧
When you're young, that's just right.
年輕人就該那樣啊
Would you stop treating me like a child?
可以不要把我當成小孩嗎？
It's embarrassing!
這樣很不自在！
Why did you cover my eyes in front of the monsters anyway?
而且你幹嘛在魔物前遮住我的眼睛？
It helped in hindsight, but still!
雖然就結果來看是幫了大忙！
Well, Chilchuck…
這樣啊，奇爾查克
You mentioned your father had passed away.
你說過父親已經不在人世了對吧？
What about it?
怎麼了嗎？
I see.
這樣啊
This seems like a good opportunity, so I'll teach you something.
機會正好，老夫也教你一些事吧
Take a seat.
在那邊坐好
You're probably getting to that age where you're starting to get curious,
畢竟你應該也到了會好奇的年紀
but it's important to have the correct information.
必須具備正確的知識才行
What's this about?
所以你要說什麼？
You see, humans
人類啊
also have stamens and pistils.
也有雄蕊與雌蕊…
That's not it! Again!
不對！再來一次！
Pay attention!
要認真聽！
And so, they passed the night away.
他們就這樣度過了一夜
Come on. Hurry.
來，快點
Not like that!
無禮之徒！
I didn't want to touch you in a weird way.
我擔心摸法要是怪怪的會不太好
Don't let stuff like that bother you!
別讓那種事情擾亂你！
Give me your left hand.
伸出左手
See? Just like this.
看吧，像這樣就行了
Feeling embarrassed won't help you improve your magic skills.
害羞是不會讓魔法進步的喔
Now focus!
集中精神…
Be mindful of the magic coursing through your body,
感受魔力在身體內部循環
like blood through your veins.
就像是血管那樣
Let it flow through the palms of your hands,
讓魔力的流動透過手掌
from the top of your head to the tips of my toes.
從你的頭頂連接至我的腳尖
Sync your breathing, temperature, and pulse with mine.
讓我們的呼吸、體溫和脈搏同步
Once you're ready, repeat after me.
當你做好準備後，跟著我複誦
-Sperae…
-斯帕拉葉…
-Yeptum…
-耶普圖姆…
-Rufermus…
-盧非姆斯…
-Vilal…
-維拉魯…
-Eurekant…
-幽雷亢特…
-Oonzu…
-尤烏滋…
That's itchy!
好癢啊！
It's itching like crazy!
超癢的…
A-Are you okay?
你還好嗎？
My scab came off.
結痂掉了！
It worked!
成功了！
You did it, Laios!
你辦到了，萊歐斯！
Really?
是嗎？
You're bleeding, though.
但你流血了耶
This is normal for your first try.
一開始都會這樣啦
But you're a fast learner.
但你學得很快
Maybe you really do come from a talented line!
你們家族的人或許真的挺有天分的！
The way you explained things made it easy to understand.
你的教法也很好懂，非常傑出
Thanks.
謝謝
Well then, before you forget this feeling,
那麼現在，趁你還沒忘記那個感覺
let's try healing Senshi.
拿先西來試試看吧
I'll be watching, so repeat what you did just now.
我會在旁邊看著 你就照剛才那樣做一次
Now, it's a temporary fix,
好，來暫時應急
but I'll use Dryad twigs to repair my staff.
用樹精的樹枝進行修復吧
I hope it attaches.
不曉得合不合用
-That felt weird. -S-Sorry!
-那種摸法好怪 -抱歉！
Like I said, don't let stuff like that bother you!
就說了，別讓那種事情擾亂你！
Don't be embarrassed.
來，不要害羞
Feeling shy is the biggest obstacle to progress!
羞恥心可是進步的頭號敵人喔！
Actually, you shouldn't underestimate things like that.
其實那種事不容小覷
Healers interact a lot with people, which can cause difficulties.
治療師會經常接觸其他人 進而引發麻煩
The main reason parties break up is often due to relationship issues.
隊伍解散通常都是因為人際關係
Falling in and out of love, envy, jealousy,
動情迷戀、嫉妒吃醋
grudges and hatred.
仇恨加上厭惡
They can be a real hassle.
有夠煩人的
Are you talking about Falin and Shuro?
你是在說法琳和修洛嗎？
I'm just speaking from my own experiences.
這只是經驗談
A leader needs the ability to unite people more than combat skills.
比起戰鬥技巧 隊長更需要團結眾人的能力
To be honest, I want Laios to focus on developing his social skills
老實說，與其要萊歐斯學魔法 我更希望他去培養
and his ability to read people more than magic.
社交技巧或看人的眼光
If he had done so, he wouldn't have unknowingly ended up
若他有那麼做就不會一回過神就發現
being an accomplice in black magic.
自己成了黑魔法的共犯
Well, Chilchuck, why don't you learn a bit about magic yourself?
我才想勸你呢 奇爾查克，你嘗試學習魔法如何？
Maybe your ignorance is making you afraid.
你會害怕是因為有既定印象吧？
Well, sorry about that!
是喔，那還真是抱歉
Many of my kin got kidnapped by elves and never came back,
我有很多同族 只因為與黑魔法的物品扯上關係
just because they were involved with some black magic artifact.
就被精靈綁架，再也回不來
That's why I never got the chance to learn more about magic.
所以才沒機會仔細去了解
So forgive me if I'm ignorant.
我這麼無知，真是不好意思啊
To sum up the ancient magic I'm studying,
我在研究的古代魔法粗略來說
it draws energy from another dimension where infinity exists.
是從存在著“無限”的異次元 提取能量的魔法
How do you turn a cup of water into vapor?
要把一杯水變成氣體該怎麼做？
By bringing it to a boil.
讓它沸騰就行了對吧？
Well then, how do you vaporize an entire lake?
那要如何把整座湖裡的水變成氣體？
The theory is the same,
雖然理論是相同的
but actually doing it is a bit tricky.
但有點難實現
This magic would require an enormous amount of power and time.
對需要極大力量 與時間的魔法加以輔助
So, you reinforce it with coordinate magic.
那就是座標魔法
This dungeon is connected to the other dimension at multiple points.
這座迷宮到處都與異次元相連
It's through this power that monsters are summoned and this dungeon is formed.
是借助那股力量召喚魔物 創造出這樣的迷宮
Earlier, Falin no longer had the strength to revive herself.
當時法琳已經沒有力量能夠自我治癒
So I rewrote a section of the dungeon
所以我局部改寫了迷宮
to make her body a part of the dungeon.
讓她的肉體成為迷宮的一部分
Only for a brief moment, of course.
當然只是短暫的一瞬間
Another rumbling.
又是地鳴
It's close.
距離好近
Look over there!
你們看那邊！
The wall is crumbling.
牆壁在動
Where are the bricks going?
要移去哪裡？
How about we take a closer look?
要不要靠近點看？
Huh?
奇怪？
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
I-I suddenly feel dizzy.
我的頭突然好暈
You might be experiencing mana sickness because you used magic for the first time.
你可能是因為第一次使用魔力 所以引發魔力暈
It should pass soon.
應該很快就會好轉
We're leaving you behind.
我們就把你留在這囉
Stay put, okay?
好好休息，知道嗎？
Whether my eyes are shut or open, all I see are lurid colors.
不管是閉眼或睜眼 都能看到鮮豔的彩色
Help.
救救我
Let me die.
讓我死吧
The magician…
把魔術師…
Am I hallucinating? Am I hearing things?
這是幻覺？幻聽？
Please, let me die.
拜託，讓我死吧
Mana sickness sucks.
魔力暈糟透了
The path is shifting.
那邊的路在改變
It feels like we're starting to grasp a pattern, but then again, not quite.
好像能抓出規律，又好像抓不到
We'll need to observe for a little longer.
看來還需要再觀察一下
It's frustrating that we can't make much progress, but…
雖然行動困難很吃不消…
The platform is rising!
地面正在上升！
Get off!
快下去…
Ow!
好痛！
That was close.
真是危險…
We almost lost our way back.
我們差點就回不去了
Carrier of a cruel, petrifying venom,
冷酷的石毒生物
the Cockatrice.
雞蛇
It's like a Basilisk!
長得好像巴西利斯克！
But a Cockatrice is much worse!
雞蛇比牠危險好幾倍！
Never let it bite you!
絕對別被咬到！
You'll be turned to stone!
不然會變成石像！
There's a door on the left!
左邊有門！
Let's get in there!
衝進裡面！
What's our plan now?
該怎麼辦才好？
This door won't hold for very long.
這樣撐不了多久
Can we sneak out through the back?
沒辦法從後面偷偷逃走嗎？
If this thing is anything like a Basilisk,
如果牠和巴西利斯克特性相似
it should sense us by our body heat.
那對方很有可能是靠體溫在識別我們
It will be tricky to give it the slip.
很難偷偷甩掉雞蛇
But that's the ability of the serpent.
不過那是蛇頭的能力
The rooster head should rely on its vision.
鳥頭應該是仰賴視力看東西
Marcille, do you remember how Laios took down the Basilisk last time?
瑪露希爾，你記得萊歐斯 上次是怎麼打倒巴西利斯克的吧？
Don't let it frighten you!
絕對不要畏縮！
Intimidate the Cockatrice with all your heart and soul!
要全心全力去威嚇對方！
Easier said than done.
說起來容易，做起來難啊
Make yourself look big and shout at the top of your lungs!
重點就是放大肢體動作 然後竭盡所有力氣大喊！
Sure, I might be the tallest of the three,
我的確是我們之中最高的
but that Cockatrice is twice as big as the Basilisk.
但對手是上次的兩倍大啊
And I'm not confident about shouting either.
而且我也不擅長大喊
Wait, how did Laios shout again?
等等，萊歐斯當時是喊什麼來著？
Was it like a yell?
是大叫“哇”？
Or more like a roar?
還是嘶吼一聲？
Never mind. If I can frighten it, that's all that matters!
算了，總之能讓對方害怕就行了！
The end.
劇終
This won't work.
這行不通啦
I just know I'll fail!
絕對會失敗！
There's no way I can do what Laios did.
萊歐斯我模仿不來！
So what do I do?
我該怎麼做才好？
I'll have to do it
我就採用
my own way!
自己的做法好了！
The most brilliant female student in the school's history,
學校有史以來最優秀的才女
Marcille!
瑪露希爾！
What was that explosion just now?
剛才的爆炸聲是什麼？
It's Marcille! Let's go!
是瑪露希爾！上吧！
Too shallow.
太淺了
Oh no. I drew too much attention to myself.
糟糕，我太顯眼了！
Now both heads are focused on me.
兩顆頭都在提防我？
I don't have time to finish an incantation.
來不及詠唱咒語了！
Marcille! Did it bite you?
瑪露希爾！你被咬了？
I'm okay.
我沒事
It bit you, you idiot!
你被咬了啊，笨蛋！
For crying out loud!
真是的！
What? You got bitten by a Cockatrice?
什麼？你被雞蛇咬了？
This is bad.
大事不妙啊
Do you know what to do when you're bitten by a Cockatrice?
你知道被雞蛇咬後的處置方式嗎？
There's a procedure for that?
有那種方法？
First, take off your pants.
首先，脫掉褲子
Sit with your legs tightly closed.
配上肌膚緊貼的坐姿
Keep your arms to your sides and cover your ears with your hands.
手臂夾緊，用手指蓋住耳朵
Close your mouth too.
嘴巴也要閉上
Perfect.
完美
Now you're all set to turn into stone at any moment.
這下隨時石化都不用擔心了
I thought the procedure was supposed to prevent that!
原來不是避免石化的處置方式？
She got petrified in an awfully precarious position.
她以十分危險的姿勢石化了啦
Something might break.
感覺身體容易斷掉
Her center of gravity is off, so she might topple any second.
而且重心還歪一邊 看起來隨時都會倒
This is bad.
完蛋了
Being turned to stone is the last thing a human could want.
是人都不會想變成這樣吧
What are we going to do?
這下要怎麼辦？
Is there a way to reverse it?
有解除石化的方法嗎？
There are a couple of ways.
方法有很多
First, we could wait for her to heal naturally.
第一種是等待自然治癒
Apparently, petrification is more of a curse than the effects of a poison.
被石化與其說是中毒 似乎更接近一種詛咒
Elves have strong resistance to spells,
精靈的魔法抗性強
so she should recover faster compared to other races.
應該會治癒得比其他種族快吧
Next, we can try finding other adventurers who might have herbs
第二種是尋找治療石化的藥草
or know-how to reverse petrification.
或是其他擁有治癒手段的冒險者
Lastly, I could give it a shot with a healing spell.
最後一種辦法是 由我來努力詠唱治療魔法
You?
你嗎？
Marcille taught me how to read the book of magic.
瑪露希爾有教我魔法書的讀法
There should be a spell in there to reverse petrification.
書上應該也會有解除石化的咒語
Let's keep an eye out for herbs and other adventurers,
總之我們去找藥草和冒險者
while also giving the other two options a try.
同時也試試看另外兩種方法吧
How long will it take for her to heal?
自然治癒大概要花多久？
It takes anywhere from six months to ten years for a tall-man.
長身人的話是半年至十年
I'll go fetch the Cockatrice.
老夫去取回雞蛇
They got pretty discolored in one night.
一個晚上就變色不少
I need to process them quickly.
得盡早處理才行
She looks like she's about to fall over.
她歪歪的，感覺好危險喔
Shouldn't we put something under her?
是不是在她屁股底下 墊個東西比較好？
You're right.
說得也是
I've got a good idea.
老夫有個好點子
Mix the julienned buds with seasoning and place them in a pot.
把花蕾切成絲 與調味料混合後鋪在鍋底
Then, put Marcille on top.
再放上瑪露希爾
Oops, her eyelashes broke off.
哎呀，她的睫毛斷了
Soak the Cockatrice meat in salt water,
以鹽水浸泡雞蛇肉
place it on Marcille's lap, and let it rest.
放在瑪露希爾的腳上，安置一陣子
I suppose her position is more stable now.
看起來是有比較穩了
She shouldn't topple over anymore.
這樣她就不會倒下了吧
She looks like some idol from a pagan religion.
好像某個邪教信奉的神像喔
After that, Laios and his team worked hard.
在那之後，萊歐斯等人非常努力
DAY 2
（第二天）
They continued with trial and error.
他們反覆嘗試和失敗
DAY 3
（第三天）
And on the fourth day…
到了第四天…
Found one!
找到了！
How do you use it?
這要怎麼用？
Why don't we try
總之呢
placing it on her?
先貼上去看看
The stone is starting to warm with my body heat.
體溫讓石化的皮膚變溫了
Let's try the spell.
開始詠唱吧
Sperae Yeptum
斯帕拉葉耶普圖姆
Rufermus Vilal…
盧非姆斯維拉魯…
Am I pronouncing it correctly?
我的發音正確嗎？
Watch out!
危險！
Marcille!
瑪露希爾！
You're soft again.
好軟
It worked!
成功了！
Huh?
什麼啊？
What's going on?
怎麼回事？
Why do I have vegetable slices on me?
為什麼有蔬菜切片？
And what's with this pot?
為什麼有鍋子？
Let's see.
老夫看看
This worked too.
這邊也順利成功了
-Hurray! -Will someone explain?
-好耶！ -這到底是怎樣啊？
Boil the brined meat
煮浸泡過鹽的肉
and cut it into thin slices.
切成薄片
Dress it with fermented buds,
配上發酵後的花蕾
and it's done.
就完成了
EISBEIN-STYLE COCKATRICE AND SAUERKRAUT-STYLE DRYAD BUDS
（水煮豬腳風雞蛇肉 與樹精花蕾酸菜）
It's been that long?
過了這麼久？
In the end, what did the trick?
結果是什麼奏效啊？
We tried so many things, who can say for sure?
試過太多方法，無法確定呢
I hope it was my spell.
希望是我唸的咒語
Nah, I say it was the fresh herbs that did it.
才怪，我看是因為藥草很新鮮吧
Maybe the cooked Cockatrice meat neutralized the curse.
會不會是烹調後的 雞蛇肉中和了詛咒？
We need to get back to the surface as soon as possible,
在必須盡快返回地表的時候
and yet I delayed us all.
我卻給他們添麻煩
You guys, I'm sor--
大家，對不…
No, that's not it.
不，不是這句
There's something else I should say in this situation.
這時還有其他更該說的話
Yes, first, I should say…
沒錯，首先要說…
You shouldn't use someone as a fermentation weight.
不要把人視作壓醬菜的石頭啦
Be that as it may, dungeon food.
無論如何，這便是迷宮飯
Oh, dungeon food.
哦，迷宮飯
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻譯：沈庭葦